since my last video about the biggest
number that can fit in a text message
some even larger numbers have been
found but let's not get ahead of
ourselves because you guys had a lot of
questions that I need to answer first
for this to make sense and if you
haven't seen that last video then make
sure to watch that
first I saw a ton of comments about Busy
Beavers and other similar functions like
reo's number or even utter Oblivion A
Busy Beaver function defines a number
based on the largest value you can get
by using a limited number of symbols or
states which was exactly what I was
trying to do in that first video in fact
there's already a Lambda Busy Beaver
function for binary Lambda calculus so
that's the answer right is this the
largest number that can fit in a text
message yes but not so fast for
something to count as the largest number
at least by my rules there needs to be
some kind of instruction or program to
generate that number but these other
functions are uncomputable they just
declare the number exists obviously but
you have no way of knowing how big it
really is or how you would produce that
number so it's hard to really call this
a number it's more like a placeholder
where the number would go when it's
discovered and and proving that a number
is a busy beaver is very difficult did
you know that the five-state turing
machine Busy Beaver was only proven this
year in
2024 and it's unlikely that a six-state
busy beaver will ever be proven In Our
Lifetime another popular comment I got
was why don't you just take the largest
number and add one or Square it or do
something crazy with
it technically it will make the number
larger but it isn't a larger number
class so for example if we were only
able to use up Arrow notations it
doesn't matter how you arrange them or
how many times you repeat them you'll
never reach a number from a higher
number class using up arrows because you
would still need more space than the
observable universe to write it down all
this other garbage here doesn't really
matter because it doesn't move the
needle at all on whatever kind of super
log SC we're using to compare big
numbers so when I say the biggest number
I mean the biggest class of number this
is not a scale we're accustomed to
thinking in so I can see how that can
come across as confusing if you want to
build up some more of that mathematical
thinking then check out today's sponsor
brilliant my son actually loves
brilliant he's taking the course right
now on Infinities which is just one of
the many courses brilliant offers
brilliant compreh comprehensive range of
math courses really are built for
Learners of any level from brushing up
on fundamentals to advanced concepts
each lesson is filled with Hands-On
problem solving that lets you play with
the concepts a method proven to make
learning six times more effective than
just watching videos in lessons you can
work on in just minutes every day it's
easy to learn anywhere on your phone
laptop whenever you have time and it's
completely free to try for 30 days so if
you're on the fence it's super easy to
just give it a try just remember to use
the URL brilliant.org codep parade so
you'll get the 20% discount if you
decide to sign up for the premium
subscription thanks
brilliant all right now let's start
where we left off last time because
there's a reason the buck hole's ordinal
function compresses so well there's a
really simple and elegant algorithm
using nuclear array notation which kind
of plays out like a Hydra game so
imagine your Hercules and you need to
defeat a Hydra how many chops does it
take this kind of Hydra is restricted to
Binary trees meaning each node is either
a head or a two-way split and there's
two rules for how to cut heads first if
the left branch is a single head you can
always chop it causing the right side to
become the new root so we can Define the
natural numbers like this where where
Stacks n heads tall Take N
[Music]
Cuts but what about when the left branch
is a tree in this case the second rule
says we need to just recursively play
the Hydra game on the left node and when
we get the result we search to find any
instances of the right branch and
replace them all with a copy of the
entire
tree now it might sound like this would
create hydras that could grow forever
ever but surprisingly any Hydra like
this can always be defeated in a finite
number of
steps and making a Hydra of this form
that's n heads tall grows at the rate of
the buck hole's ordinal function which
is a lot faster than the tree function
there's a stack Overflow post by Pat
kale that goes over the proofs and a lot
more detail so I'll link that below
because it's a really fun
read okay now it's time to reveal what
the newest largest number is this next
number comes from bashu Matrix system or
BMS this is a really powerful notation
but it's also more difficult to explain
and program because it has more rules
for the reductions and that's why it
took a while to translate to Binary
Lambda calculus but by using a really
clever data representation it was
eventually finished by none other than
the same Pat kale who managed to fit it
in under 52 bytes of BLC which is even
smaller than the buck holes ordinal
function we came up with
before so how fast does BMS grow well
with a single row called A Primitive
sequence system the function has a
growth rate of Epsilon knot BMS with two
rows is called a pair sequence system
and the growth rate ordinal is
equivalent to the buck holes ordinal
where we left off last time what about
three rows or four or or n
rows well now we run into the issue of
running out of standard ordinals for the
notation so I'm going to switch to a
different system to represent larger
ordinals called proof theoretic ordinals
or
pto's I'm going to warn you now this is
the part of the video where things start
getting tricky to explain I had to do so
much research to learn this stuff and I
still barely understand a lot of it but
bear with me it's worth it so let me
explain what proof theoretic ordinals
are whenever we prove theorems we use a
system of axioms and rules for deduction
and depending on which axioms we start
with we can get different proof systems
these proof systems each have different
strengths which correspond directly to
ordinals you can think of the proof
theoretic ordinal as the limit for the
largest level of recursion you can use
to prove statements in that system so
for example Pano arithmetic or first
order arithmetic has the proof theoretic
ordinal Epsilon KN the Buckle's ordinal
happens to be the proof theoretic
ordinal for this system which is a
strong subset of second order
arithmetic diagonalizing BMS is proven
to be larger than that but less than or
equal to full second order arithmetic so
it's definitely a larger class of
number but we're not done yet there's
still an even larger number that was
ported to Lambda calculus recently and
that's loader's number you see second
order arithmetic has the same PTO as
system F which is the typed Lambda
calculus and beyond that we have system
F Omega where the types can have types
recursively and after that is the more
expressive calculus of constructions it
has the really nice property of being
strongly normalizing that means if you
think of the proof system like a
programming language all programs are
guaranteed to terminate so we're
actually able to iterate over all
possible programs of a given length and
add up their run times to get a truly
massive number this isn't normally
possible in regular Lambda calculus
because of the halting problem which
means programs can run forever and never
terminate so how much space does loaders
number take in BLC well John Trump no
not that one was able to optimize it and
create a number that exceeds loaders
number in
233 bytes which unfortunately doesn't
fit into a text
message but it does fit nicely into a
tweet if you're using Unicode so that's
still really cool and believe it or not
that's the largest computable number
class proven so far for real this time
there are bigger proof theoretic
ordinals for systems like zfc and some
fast growing functions like greedy click
sequences are claimed to reach that
growth but none of these have been
rigorously proven yet so it looks like
we're at the end of our journey for now
that's the largest number class that's
proven so far regardless of size
limitations at least until there's some
new breakthrough I hope this is a much
more satisfying answer huge thanks to
the googology community for helping me
research this topic and thanks for
watching